Guide to The Leo Deaner Radical Left-Wing Publications collection, 1890-2017 LAC0011
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
The Leo Deaner Radical Left-Wing Publications collection
1890-2017
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
Deaner, Leo
LAC0011
94 Linear Feet
This collection is composed of 20th and early 21st century American radical Left-Wing publication material. It is comprised mainly of various printed material, including pamphlets, newsletters, journals and flyers dating from 1890-2017. The individuals and groups represented in these publications were active in the American labor, anti-war, black power and radical student movements. Many of them espoused a proletarian revlutionary agenda. In 2009, Leo Deaner donated a collection of books and pamphlets related to the radical left-wing movements in America. Numerous donations followed this initial one. The books donated by Mr. Deaner are cataloged and housed in the Special Collections book collection. For locating these books use the GW Libraries online catalog. The pamphlets, flyers, and newsletters donated by Mr. Deaner became this collection. To compliment and deepen the research value of Mr. Deaner's donations the Labor History Research Center staff have purchased additional materials and added them to this collection. Leo Deaner is a longtime trade unionist and political activist. He joined Teamsters Local 776 located in Harrisburg, Pennsylvania in 1968 after serving in the US Army. He served the local as an elected Business Agent for a number of years. While attending Harrisburg Area Community College and the University of California at Berkeley he played leadership roles in the progressive movements of that era. Most recently Mr. Deaner has served since 1999 as a senior staff member of the International Brotherhood of Teamsters reporting directly to the General President.
Scope and Contents
This collection, composed of material from a number of different sources, offers researchers a unique look at the 20th and early 21st century American Left. It is comprised mainly of various printed material, including pamphlets, newsletters, journals and flyers dating from 1890-2017.
Arrangement
Organized into five series: Pamphlets by title: Old Left [arrangement aphabetical], Pamphlets by title: Old Left [arrangement loosely chronological], Pamphlets by title: New Left [arrangement alphabetical], Pamphlets by title: New Left [arrangement chronological], and Pamphlets by topic
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for research.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The core of this collection is a series of donations made by Leo Deaner beginning in in 2009. Over the course of three years Mr. Deaner donated a significant number of books and pamphlets on the New Left and the Black Liberation and anti-Vietnam War movements. This orignal donation from Mr. Deaner has been made subsequent donations multiple times per year since 2015 of purchased pamphlets.
Bib#
15914783 MMS ID# 99159147833604107
Newspapers; Radicals; Protest movements; Communism; Black Liberation; Civil rights; Socialism; Women's rights; Vietnam War, 1961-1975 -- Protest movements -- United States; Student movements; Marxism-Leninism; New Communist movement; X, Malcolm, 1925-1965; Davis, Angela Y. (Angela Yvonne), 1944-
- Pamphlets by title: Old Left [arrangement alphabetical], 1910-1959; Series 1
  Arrangement
  This series is arranged alphabetically.
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains radical left wing publications dating from 1910-1959. Roughly falling into the category of the "Old Left," the majority of these pamphlets and journals were published by the Communist Party, USA, the Socialist Party, USA and the Socialist Labor Party. Others were published by the Young People's Socialist League, the Communist League, and the Workers Party.
  The topics covered in the publications vary, but most are related in some way to communist and socialist thought on labor, capitalism and the working class; some are party propaganda and recruitment tools while others lay out more theoretical arguments. Also included are publications related to the Second Red Scare, including Senate reports and pamphlets advocating for the civil liberties of communists and socialists, and materials opposing the United States' involvement in World War II. Other pamphlets detail the history of the labor movement, communist party and the international labor holiday known as May Day. Also of particular note are six issues of "The New Masses" magazine, dating from 1934-1936, including an issue from May Day, 1934.
  Also worth noting in this series are the numerous publications authored by important communist and socialist figures of the day. These include Daniel DeLeon, Mary Marcy, William Z. Foster and Earl Browder.
  - "13 Communists Speak to the Court", 1953; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    General
    Published by New Century Publishers.
    McCarthyism; Communist Party of the United States of America
  - "Amnesty!", 1952 December; Series 1 (Box 19, Folder 1)
    Author: Marion Bachrach. Published by New Century Publishers.
  - "Are You Ready for War?", undated; Series 1 (Box 19, Folder 31)
    Author: Hal Draper. Published by the Young People's Socialist League.
    Young People's Socialist League
  - "The Big Lie of War 'Prosperity'", 1952; Series 1 (Box 19, Folder 2)
    Author: Bernard Burton. Published by New Century Publishers.
    Communist Party of the United States of America
  - "Can Everybody Be Rich and Still Be Honest?", 1951 April; Series 1 (Box 19, Folder 3)
    Author: Jim West. Published by the Communist Party, USA.
  - "The Cartel System", 1946; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Author: James S. Allen
    Published by International Publishers.
  - "The Church and the Workers", 1932; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Author: Bennett Stevens
    Prepared under the direction of the Labor Research Association. Published by International Pamphlets.
    Labor Research Association (U.S.)
  - "The C.I.O. Today", 1950; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Author: George Morris
  - "Civil Rights Congress Tells the Story", undated; Series 1 (Box 19, Folder 4)
    Issued by the Civil Rights Congress.
    Civil rights; Civil Rights Congress
  - "Communism in American Trade Unions", undated; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Author: Philip Taft
    Reprinted from Proceedings of the Sixth Annual Meeting, Industrial Relations Research Association
    Industrial Relations Research Association
  - "Communism and Christianism: Analyzed and Contrasted from the Marxian and Darwinian Points of View", 1926; Series 1 (Box 19, Folder 5)
    Author: Bishop William Montgomery Brown. Published by the Bradford-Brown Educational Company.
  - "The Communist: A Magazine of the Theory and Practice of Marxism-Leninism", 1931 January - June; Series 1 (Box 19, Folder 32)
    Published by the Communist Party, USA.
  - "Communist Call to the Toiling Farmer", 1931; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Published for the Communist Party of USA by Workers Library Publishers.
  - "Communist Domination of Certain Unions" Senate Report, 1952; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    Report of the Subcommittee on Labor and Labor-Management Relations of the Committee on Labor and Public Welfare, United States Senate
    United States. Congress. Senate
  - "Communist Election Platform 1938", Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    Published for Ohio State Committee, Communist Party by Workers Library Publishers, Inc.
  - "The Communist Party in Action", 1932; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    Author: Alex Bittelman
    Published by Workers Library Publishers.
  - "The Communist Party Manifesto", 1919; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - "The Communist Party of the USA: Its History, Role and Organization", 1943; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    Author: Earl Browder
  - "The Communist Position in 1936", Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    Earl Browder radio speech, broadcast March 5, 1936
  - "Communists and the Trade Unions", 1943; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    Author: Roy Hudson
  - "The Concentration of Wealth", 1907; Series 1 (Box 19, Folder 6)
    Author: Henry Laurens Call. Published by the Chandler Publishing Company.
  - "A Congressman Can Do Something About War! Says Bob Brenneman Our Candidate for Congress", 1950; Series 1 (Box 19, Folder 7)
    Published by the United Labor Paty of America.
    American Labor Party
  - "The Coolidge Program: Capitalist Democracy and Prosperity Exposed", 1927; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    Author: Jay Lovestone
  - "Danger Signals for Organized Labor", 1953; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    Author: William Z. Foster
  - "Declaration of Communist and Workers Parties of Socialist Countries", 1957 December; Series 1 (Box 19, Folder 8)
  - "The Democratic Front: For Jobs, Security, Democracy and Peace", 1938; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    Author: Earl Browder, General Secretary, Communist Party USA
    Published by Workers Library Publishing.
  - "Destroy Hitler! Free Germany! An Appeal of the German Communists", 1942; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - "Dolje Kaptializam! Proturatni Govori", undated; Series 1 (Box 19, Folder 9)
    Author: Eugene Debs.
    Socialist Party of the United States of America
  - "Don't Look the Other Way! The McCarren Law is Aimed at You Too!", 1950s; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    Published by the Citizens Committee for Constitutional Liberties
    Citizens Committee for Constitutional Liberties
  - "The End of the Ford Myth", 1932; Series 1 (Box 19, Folder 10)
    Author: Robert Cruden. Published by International Pamphlets.
  - "The Federal Jury is Stacked Against You", 1949 January; Series 1 (Box 22, Folder 10)
    Author: Marion Bachrach. Published by the Communist Party Defense Committee.
  - "The First Amendment or the Last Liberty", 1950s; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    Author: James E. Jackson, Editor, The Worker
  - "Five Men on a Hunger Strike", 1948; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    Authors: Charles A. Doyle, Gerhart Eisler, Irving Potash, Ferdinand C. Smith and John Williamson
    Published by the Civil Rights Congress and the American Commitee for Protection of Foreign Born
    Civil Rights Congress; American Committee for Protection of Foreign Born
  - "For a Cost-Plus Wage", 1943 October; Series 1 (Box 19, Folder 33)
    Author: Max Shachtman. Published by the Workers Party.
    Communism
  - "For A Powerful United A. F. of L.", 1936; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    Statement of Central Committee, Communist Party USA
    Printed by District 2, Communist Party.
  - "For Abolition of the Inquisitorial Committee of Congress", 1957; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    Author: Harvey O'Connor
    Published by the Emergency Civil Liberties Committee.
    Emergency Civil Liberties Committee
  - "Foundations of Leninism", 1939; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 23)
    Author: Joseph Stalin
    Published by International Publishers
  - "Freedom = Security", 1957; Series 1 (Box 19, Folder 11)
    Author: Harry Cain. Published by the Trade Union Program on Civil Liberties and Rights.
  - "Freedom is Everybody's Job! The Crime of the Government Against the Negro People", 1940s; Series 1 (Box 19, Folder 12)
    Author: George Crockett, Jr. Published by the National Non-Partisan Committee To Defend the Rights of the 12 Communist Leaders.
    Civil rights; McCarthyism
  - "From Young Socialists to Young Communists", 1934; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    Authors: George Smerkin and Sol Larks
    Published by Young Worker, Offical Organ of the Young Communist League, USA.
  - "The Geography of Capitalism", 1938; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 25)
    Author: W.G. Moore
    Published as part of The New People's Library, Left Book Club Edition.
    Left Book Club Co-operative
  - "Going Left: The Left Wing Formulates a 'Draft for a Program for the Socialist Party of the United States'", 1936; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Hearings before the Committee on Un-American Activities, 1957 March 26-27; Series 1 (Box 19, Folder 13)
    McCarthyism; United States. Congress. House. Committee on Un-American Activities
  - "The Historic Fight to Abolish School Segregation in the United States", 1954; Series 1 (Box 19, Folder 14)
    Author: Doxey Wilkerson. Published by the Jefferson School of Social Science.
    Civil rights; Communist Party of the United States of America
  - "History of the Communist Party of the United States", 1952; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 27)
    Published by the Jefferson School of Social Science.
  - "History of May Day", 1934; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 28)
    Author: Alexander Trachtenberg
    Published by International Pamphlets.
  - "How Capitalism Has Hypnotized Society", 1910s; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 29)
    Author: William Thurston Brown
    Published for the Socialist Party, USA by Charles H. Kerr & Co.
  - "How the Farmer Can Get His", 1916; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 30)
    Author: Mary Marcy
    Published by Charles H. Kerr & Co.
  - "How to Get Jobs for All", 1945; Series 1 (Box 19, Folder 34)
    Published by the Workers Party Election Campaign Committee.
  - "If We Remain Silent...", 1949; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 31)
    Published for the United Defense Committee Against "Loyalty" Checks by Acme Press.
    McCarthyism; United Defense Committee against loyalty checks
  - "Industrial Unionism and Social Construction", 1937 March; Series 1 (Box 19, Folder 15)
    Author: Glen Carothers.
  - "The International Socialist Review" Magazine, 1917 January; Series 1 (Box 19, Folder 16)
  - "Introduction to Philosophy", 1938; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 32)
    Author: John Lewis
  - "Is Communism Un-American? 9 Questions About the Communist Party Answered", 1947; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 33)
    Author: Eugene Dennis
  - "Jobs Not Battleships!", 1940 January; Series 1 (Box 22, Folder 1)
    Author: Dwight MacDonald. Published by the Socialist Workers Party.
  - "Labor Conscription: Involuntary Servitude of Labor", 1943; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 34)
    Author: Arnold Peterson
    Published for the Socialist Labor Party by New York Labor News Company.
    Socialist Labor Party
  - "Labor Faces '44's Challenge", 1944; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 35)
    Author: Joseph North
  - "A Labor Party for the United States", 1936; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 36)
    Published by the Social Economic Foundation
  - "Let's Keep the Tools of Plenty: Big Busines Must Not Get Government War Plans", 1944 November; Series 1 (Box 19, Folder 17)
    Author: Lewis Corey. Published by the Post War World Council.
    Post War World Council
  - "A Letter to American Negroes", 1948 September; Series 1 (Box 19, Folder 18)
    Author: William Bohannan. Published by Pioneer Publishers for the Socialist Workers Party.
    Civil rights; Communism; Socialist Workers Party
  - "Man Bites Dog: Report of an Unusual Hearing Before the McCarran Committee", 1952; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 37)
    Published by National Guardian.
    McCarthyism
  - "The March on Washington One Year After...", 1942 June; Series 1 (Box 19, Folder 19)
    Author: Albert Parker. Published by Pioneer Publishers.
    Civil rights movements
  - "Marxism and Linguistics", 1951; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    Published as part of the Little Lenin Library by International Publishers.
  - "Masses and Mainstream" Journal, 1949 October; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - "May Day 1940", Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    Author: Louis F. Budenz
    Published by Workers Library Publishers
    May Day
  - "May Day vs. Labor Day", 1936; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    Author: Olive M. Johnson
    Published for the Socialist Labor Party by the New York Labor News Co.
    May Day; Labor Day; Socialist Labor Party
  - "Merrie England: Letters to John Smith, Workingman", undated; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    Author: Robert Blatchford, with introduction by Eugene V. Debbs
  - "'My Friends': A Fireside Chat on the War", 1940 June; Series 1 (Box 22, Folder 2)
    Author: Native Son. Published by the Workers Party.
  - "Negro Liberation", 1932; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    Published by International Pamphlets
    Civil rights; National liberation movements; Communist Party of the United States of America
  - "The Negro People in the United States: Facts for All Americans", 1953; Series 1 (Box 22, Folder 14)
    Compiled by Howard Selsam. Published by the Jefferson School of Social Science.
  - "The New Masses" Magazine, 1934 April 17 - 1936 March 24; Series 1 (Oversize 4, Folder 1)
  - "The Next Steps in the Struggle for Negro Freedom", 1953; Series 1 (Box 19, Folder 20)
    Author: Hugh Bradley. Published by New Century Publishers.
  - "On Historical Materialism", 1940; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    Author: Frederick Engels
    Published as part of the Little Marx Library by International Publishers.
  - "On to Washington for Negro Rights", 1941 June; Series 1 (Box 22, Folder 3)
    Author: Henry Pelham. Published by the Workers Party.
  - "Organized Labor and the Fascist Danger", 1947; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - "Outlook for a New Labor Advance", undated; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    Published by The New Press Publishers, Inc.
  - "The Path of a Renegade: Why Earl Browder Was Expelled from the Communist Party", 1946; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    Author: Robert Thompson
  - "Plain Talk on War", 1941 May 24; Series 1 (Box 22, Folder 4)
    Published by the Workers Party.
  - "Problems of Organized Labor Today", 1946; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - "Race Discrimination - And the Law", 1945 October; Series 1 (Box 19, Folder 21)
    Author: Carey McWilliams. Published by the National Institute for Constitutional Liberties.
    McCarthyism; Civil rights
  - "The Rankin Witch Hunt", 1945; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - "Reconversion: 60,000,000 Jobs or 15,000,000 Jobless", 1945; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    Published by New Century Publishers
  - "The Record of Truman's 81st Congress", 1949; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    Author: Rob Fowler Hall, Washington Correspondent, The Daily Worker
  - "Reform or Revolution or Socialim and Socialist Politics", 1918; Series 1 (Box 19, Folder 22)
    Author: Karl Dannenberg. Published by the Radical Review Publishing Association.
  - "Report of the Fifth National Convention of the Young Communist Leage of USA", 1928; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    United States. Congress. House. Committee on Un-American Activities
  - Report of the Special Committee on Un-American Activities, 1939; Series 1 (Box 19, Folder 23)
  - "Reviling of the Great", 1949; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 16)
    Published for the Socialist Labor Party by the New York Labor News Company.
  - "The Revolter", 1917 May; Series 1 (Box 19, Folder 24)
    Edited by H. Lincoln Dale.
  - "The Right to Speak for Peace", undated; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - "The Rights of the Masses", 1910; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 18)
    A lectury by George D. Brewer
  - "Schools and the Crisis", 1934; Series 1 (Box 19, Folder 25)
    Author: Rex David. Published by International Pamphlets.
  - "Security and a Living Wage: Why Workers Strike", 1945 November; Series 1 (Box 22, Folder 5)
  - "Sikeston: Hitlerite Crime Against America", 1942; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 19)
    Speech by William H. Patterson delivered on February 15, 1942
    Published by the Communist Party of Missouri.
  - "Social Action (A Magazine of Fact)", 1942 January 15; Series 1 (Box 19, Folder 26)
    Published by the Council for Social Action of the Congregational Christian Churches.
    Social action
  - "Socialism: The World of Tomorrow", 1953; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - "Socialism Answers Anti-Semitism", 1944; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 21)
    Author: Eric Hass
  - "The Socialist Party: Last Bulwark of Capitalism", undated; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 22)
    Author: Moissaye J. Olgin
    Published for the Communist Party, USA by Workers Library Publishers.
  - "Socialist Reconstruction of Society: The Industrial Vote", 1919; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 23)
    Author: Daniel DeLeon
    Published by the Socialist Labor Party.
  - "The Socialist Spirit" Magazine, 1902 December; Series 1 (Box 19, Folder 27)
    Published by Franklin Wentworth.
  - "Some Problems of Work in Right-Led Unions", 1952; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 24)
    Author: John Swift
    Reprinted from Political Affairs, May-April 1952. Published by New Century Publishers.
  - "The Source of Communist Courage", 1944; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 25)
    Author: Jacques Duclos, Secretery of the Communist Party of France
    Published by the Communist Political Association of New York State.
    Communist Party of the United States of America -- France
  - "The Spy at Your Counter", undated; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 26)
    Author: Elizabeth Lawson
  - "Stop Franco Now! Prevent World War III - Aid Spanish Republican Underground", 1944; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 27)
    Speech of John M. Coffee in the House of Representatives, June 19, 1944
    Published by the United States Government Printing Office.
    Spain History Civil War, 1936-1939
  - "Strategy of the Communists", 1923; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 28)
    A letter from the Communist International to the Mexican Communist Party.
    Published by the Workers Party of America.
    Mexico
  - "The Strike Situation and Organized Labor's Wage and Job Strategy", 1945; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - "The Struggle Against Opportunism: An Appraisal of Daniel DeLeon", 1959; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 30)
    Author: L.G. Raisky
    Published for the Socialist Labor Party by the New York Labor New Company.
  - "The Struggle Against White Chauvinism", 1949; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 31)
    Issued by the National Education Department, Communist Party, USA
  - "Student Cadre" Journal, undated; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 32)
    Published by the Student Section of the Communist Party, USA.
  - "The Student-Worker" Magazine, 1927 March 1; Series 1 (Box 22, Folder 11)
    Published by the Student Council of the Workers' School.
  - Supreme Court Petition, Eugene Dennis, et. al. vs. USA, 1950; Series 1 (Box 19, Folder 28)
  - "Ten Years: History and Principles of the Left Opposition", 1933 January; Series 1 (Box 22, Folder 6)
    Author: Max Schachtman. Published for the Communist League of America by Pioneer Publishers.
    Communism; Communist League (U.S.)
  - "Thaddeus Stevens: Militant Democrat and Fighter for Negro Rights", 1942; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    Published by International Publishers, Inc.
  - "A Third Party", 1947; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    Issued by the Independent Progressive Party of California.
  - "The Thirty Hour Bill: Can the Economic Laws of Capitalism be Repealed by Legislative Enactment?", 1933; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    Statement of Verne L. Reynolds for the Socialist Labor Party before US Senate Judiciary Committee, January 25, 1933.
    Published by the New York Labor News Company.
  - "This Is Not Our War!", 1940s; Series 1 (Box 22, Folder 7)
  - "To Every Member of the IWO: A Message from Our President William Weiner", 1941; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    Issued by the William Weiner Solidarity Committee.
    International Workers Order
  - "The Truth About Father Coughlin", 1935; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    Author: A.B. Magil
  - "The Truth About Socialism", 1913; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    Author: Allan L. Benson
    Published by B.W. Huebsch Publisher.
  - "Treason in Congress: A Record of the Un-American Activities Committee", 1948 April; Series 1 (Box 22, Folder 12)
    Author: Albert E. Kahn. Published by the Progressive Citizens of America.
    McCarthyism; Progressive Citizens of America
  - "Unemployment and the American Working Class", undated; Series 1 (Box 22, Folder 8)
    Author: Arne Swabeck. Published for the Communist League of America by Pioneer Publishers.
    Communist League (U.S.)
  - "US Labor Looks at Europe", 1951; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 7)